Guide to the Douglas Gordon Papers WAG.256
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Douglas Gordon Papers
1951-2001
WAG.256
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
3.0 linear feet (3 boxes)
Douglas Gordon, stage manager and actor, joined the Actors’ Equity Association in 1948. He was first elected to the Association’s Council in the late 1960s and was elected again in the 1980s. More than two-thirds of his papers reflect his dual passions: social justice issues and the creation and support of a National Theatre in America. The collection includes correspondence, reports, notes, election materials, files on individual productions, files on other theatrical unions, such as the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists, and material on racial issues in the theater. He died on December 18th, 2009 at the age of 90. NOTE: This collection is stored offsite, and advance notice is required for use.
Gordon, Douglas, 1919-
Provenance
Aware that the Actors’ Equity Association collection was at the Robert F. Wagner Archives at New York University, Douglas Gordon’s wife Rose Mary contacted the Archives in the spring of 2003 and the papers were donated later that year.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. NOTE: This collection is stored offsite, and advance notice is required for use.
Historical/Biographical Note
Born in Seattle, Washington on April 7, 1919, Douglas Gordon joined Actors' Equity on July 15, 1948 with the status of "Junior" Member. After working in summer stock for three continuous summers, he applied for and received "Senior" Classification in 1950. Four years later he joined the American Federation of Television and Radio Actors (AFTRA). He was also a member of the Screen Actors Guild (SAG). He was elected to the Association's Council for the first time in the 1960s when he served on numerous committees, including Production Contract, Editorial Board, Agency, and Casting Information. He served during the 1970s and 1980s although he often had to run on petition, having been passed over by the nominating committee. With his passion for social justice he was active on the Ethnic Minorities committee and felt that "Equity's policy of support to [ sic] non-traditional casting must be vigorously pursued."
Gordon's greatest passion, demonstrated in his papers, was to secure a National Theatre here in the United States. To that end he served as the chairman of the National Theatre Committee for seven years, "during which time the final and complete Equity National Theatre plan was approved by Council and the membership." He considered "the National Theatre plan to be a singular accomplishment of Equity's." In 1987, having relocated back to his home state of Washington, he continued to wage "an unremitting campaign in the Council and the membership to save the plan from the possibility of revisions that would destroy the only National Theatre plan worth a tinker's dam [ sic] to the Equity membership and the American people." Sadly, his plan never came to fruition.
Scope and Content Note
The Douglas Gordon Papers consist of his personal files, reflecting his career in the performing arts and his interest in social justice, which he often found interconnected. One of the most striking aspects of his personal collection is his propensity for taking notes and annotating material he received or collected. Almost every article he clipped, letter he received or speech he wrote is covered in his handwritten comments.
Series I: Actors’ Equity Association Materials, 1951-2001, is comprised of Gordon’s files relevant to the Association, including general correspondence, reports, notes, clippings and other printed items and an extensive body of material on the National Theatre Committee, which he chaired for seven years.
Series II: Subject Files, 1951-1986, contains information on Gordon’s other union memberships and activities (AFTRA and SAG). This series has a major focus on his fervor for equal opportunity issues, including his work with the "Committee for the Employment of the Negro Performer."
NOTE: This collection is stored offsite, and advance notice is required for use.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
Organized into 2 series:
I, Actors’ Equity Association Materials, 1951-2001
II, Subject Files, 1951-1986
Actors' Equity Association.; American Federation of Television and Radio Artists.; Burstyn, Ellen, 1932-; Committee for the Employment of the Negro Performer.; Gordon, Douglas, 1919-; Gordone, Charles.; Grody, Don.; Munso, Felix.; Screen Actors Guild.; Actors |x Labor Unions |z United States.; Actors |z United States.; Los Angeles (Calif.); New York (N.Y.); Seattle (Wash.); Theater |x United States |x History.; Theater |x United States |x Production and direction.; Theater |z New York (State) |z New York |x History.
- Series I: Actors' Equity Association Materials, 1951-2001.
  - Agency and Casting Issues, 1958, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Actors Committee, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American National Theatre and Academy (ANTA), 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bakke (Allan) Case: Reverse discrimination, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Broadway Blackout, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Caucuses and Rank & File Movements, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: Equity and theatre related, 1961-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: General items that could affect theatre (most with notes), 1957-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings: segregation and discrimination mostly Equity and theatre related, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conflict of Interest: includes Angus Duncan meeting on stage managers, Edward Weston Letter, articles, writings and notes, 1950s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Constitution and By-Laws: marked copies, 1955, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Constitutional Amendment: Article !!, Section 12 of Actors' Equity Association's Constitution, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Gordon personal and related Equity/theatrical (includes letters from Paddy Chayefsky and George S. Kaufman, original signatures), 1950s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Gordon personal and related Equity/theatrical, 1960s, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: in support of Myron Fagin's play Red Rainbow, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: to Council, 1959-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Council Lists, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Council Minutes with handwritten notes, 1962, 1977, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Department of Education [in Equity]: correspondence, minutes, petitions, and related materials, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Deputy: Apple Cart, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Deputy: Fancy Meeting You Again, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Deputy: World of Suzie Wong, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dues Referendum, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Elections, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Elections, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Elections, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Elections, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Elections, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Equity Library Theatre (ELT), 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Fouratt, James and Western Advisory Board issues, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Future Ideas, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - General: Meeting Notices, Reports, Duplicated Correspondence, and related material, undated, 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Grody, Don/ Executive Secretary: renewal of contract and related issues, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Handwritten Materials: notes and notebooks (I), undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Handwritten Materials: notes and notebooks (II), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Labor-Management Reporting and Disclosure Act of 1959, Sep 14, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - League of Off Broadway Theatrical Employees and Technicians (LOBTET), undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Man Who Never Died(a play about Joe Hill): programs, reviews, notes, Equity News article, 1958, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Membership Meeting Transcript (partial and undated) of membership discussion period re: chairing the Merger Committee (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Munso, Felix: correspondence (from Munso only) and Council minute notes, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): AFL-CIO Policy Resolution on the National Theatre, Oct 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): Analysis of the NTC Subcommittee Interim Report with cover letter, Jan 11, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): Clippings, 1980s, 2000s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): correspondence/Jerry Brinkman (Seattle), 2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): correspondence to Council (including statements and speeches, 1983-1985, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): correspondence to/from Gordon, 1983-1985, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): dispute re: coalition steering committee, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): "Discord", 1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): Federal Theatre, People v. Elitist Theatre and related articles and materials, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): Final Report/National Theatre Research Sub-committee, Apr 25, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): general/minutes, member lists and related materials, 1972-1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): general/minutes, member lists and related materials, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): general/minutes, member lists and related materials, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): Interim Report, Dec 27, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): Interim Report Reply, Feb 1, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): mailings from/by Gordon, Mar 2000-May 2000 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): Majority Report (6/85) and Minority Report (5/85 & 5/85) for presentation to Special Council Meeting, April 10, 1986, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): National Theatre Conference, May 28, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): National Theatre Conference #2, Nov 14, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): National Theatre Conference #3, Feb 27, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): notes and background material for meeting with Seattle Councilor Barbara Calendar, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): Opposition Report/NTC version without Burstyn deletions, Jun 1985 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): Opposition Report with Burstyn corrections, Jun 1985 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): Other plans and comparative analysis including LORT (League of Resident Theatres), NEA (National Endowment for the Arts), MAB (Midwestern Advisory Board), 1979, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): political and economic considerations (research), 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - National Theatre Committee (NTC): Speech to Council, May 6, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Notes and clippings in file labeled "Equity January Meeting", 1962 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Oriental Actors of America Protest, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Production Contract Issues, 1977, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Production Contract Negotiations and Strike, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Production Contract Negotiations, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Racial discrimination/civil rights issues including Ron Ballard and Gordon correspondence with Equity, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Ratification of Contract Committee: resolutions, speech, and related materials, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Showcase Code and 99-Seat Waiver Plan, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Showcase Code Challenge, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Theatre lists by contract and related materials, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Understudies: rules in Production Contract, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Government Legislation: notes, articles, Equity resolutions, and related materials, 1977-1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1951-1981.
  - American Committee for Protection of the Foreign Born: speech, script, and thank you letter, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA): AWARE, Inc. and other materials on the blacklist, 1955-1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - AFTRA: clippings, 1950s, 1970s, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - AFTRA: general (includes materials on TvA/AFRA merger and national and NY local constitutions), 1951-1955 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - AFTRA: general (includes election materials for the "Middle-of-the-Road Group" and a resolution re: Blacklisting), 1956 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - AFTRA: general, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - AFTRA: general (includes charges of un-fair labor practices by Channel 13 and a 1960 anti-communist resolution), 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - AFTRA: general (Includes contract for The Adams Chronicles), 1972-1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - AFTRA: speeches, 1950s, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - American Theatre Wing Professional Training Program for veterans, 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Committee for the Employment of the Negro Performer (CENP): employment and casting issues, 1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - CENP: Equity Rule 23/Discrimination and related issues, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - CENP: handwritten notes and notebooks, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - CENP: meetings, committee work, and related materials, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - CENP: Newsletters, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - CENP: resolution presented by Charles Gordone (Chair) at Equity Membership Meeting, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Negro American Labor Council (NALC): materials, notes, clippings, 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Notes, letters, and manuscript re: Report on Blacklisting by John Cogley [1956], undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Poem for Adults by Adam Wazyk, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Resume, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Screen Actors Guild (SAG), 1950s (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Screen Actors Guild (SAG), 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 29)